[Music]
[Applause]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings you relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
SC radio is brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine online at computer or
/ software this is an interview on open
source development with Professor gild
from CROI who is a professor in
strategic management and innovation at
the Swiss Federal Institute of
Technology eth in series Kevin Crowe has
done a number of studies on open source
development topics including code reuse
innovation motivation and the social
practice of open source development
my name is targeting sale and this is an
interview for I Tripoli software so
working in management science how did
you become interested in open source
development well I was primarily
interested in in open source software
development because it represents an
entirely new way of innovating which
turns out to be both effective and
efficient it is an interesting model
that we heard from Hitler at MIT and
myself called private collective
innovation that means that private
contributors such as individuals and
firms provide work and software to a
public good innovation its public good
innovation because you cannot prevent
anybody from using the software and once
one person's usage of the software
doesn't really negatively interfere with
another person's use of the software so
in that sense it's public it's a public
good innovation so it represents a
fantastic incentive it's a route
fantastic solution to an incentive
problem of how to create public goods
that was the reason why I became very
interested they're examples of
phenomenas previously yes I'm in science
in some ways has some of the same
characteristics but science tend to be
more of a collective action type of
innovation that means that society for
example subsidizes scientists or you
know not only Society but also you know
private fund holders subsidized
scientists too to also create public
good innovations through the science
that they do not for example if you
write papers or if you do a laboratory
experiment that you report on this is
also becoming a good for society public
good but but here the model is slightly
different because salaries for example
are paid by the state or are paid by
powered private and governments that
allow designs to happen source software
development has has seen an incredible
development for the last decade both in
terms of the number of contributors as
well as the number of projects being
launched they if you just count the the
lines of code of open-source software
development projects you see that it's
been an explosive development the number
of people getting engaged the the
public's involvement in open-source has
been has seen a phenomenal development
if you look at repositories such as or
as development sites such as source
board for example you see that currently
there are more than 1 million people
involved in open-source software
development projects with in excess of
100,000 software projects that is not to
say that all of these actually are
successful in the sense of attracting
contributions and attracting code and
developing product or developing
products but they are part of a
phenomenon which is kind of huge in
society and that also changes the face
of the software industry to some extent
anything about how those successful
products are managed I think that we
start to know much more about the way
that open source of the projects are
organized and in the in the past we used
to think of them as as very very open
the source where everybody could
contribute everybody could contribute
comments and cold and could could fix
bugs in the software and so on and today
we know that you need in most successful
products a coherent development team
small team that takes on suggestions
from a large community of collaborators
review modules of software before
implementing them with the official
release of a software so you have
typically a very large group of of or
community of contributors and a much
smaller group of core developers that
secure the quality and the main and and
sustainability or the project I think
that management science can learn a lot
from open source of course open source
can learn from management science too
but open source shows the way for
companies that want to open up their
innovation process to the outside and
that means that they motivate people to
come up with ideas identify technologies
that they can use internally for their
own product development and we clearly
see that you know open source software
projects they tend to motivate people to
to contribute in in an outstanding way
the way that in ways that for example
companies sometimes find difficult to
emulate but companies that do try this
and do try to work with an open source
model such as IBM for example or they
are successful in using ideas and
knowledge from the outside to innovate
internally
to characterize the open source
developer the open source developer can
basically be anybody with an interest in
the functionality that the software
offers or the code or some algorithm
that can be implemented in code I think
that it used to be the fact that most
people were volunteer contributors
coming from universities perhaps having
a full time job as a software developer
in the company doing open source on
their spare time
but as this phenomenon has increased its
impact become a become bigger we also
see that today many if not even most
open-source software developers work for
companies and they do open source
development in their work time in the
reasons that they you examine motivation
yeah that's that's of course the
critical question because if we don't
understand what drives the open source
developer to contribute then we don't
know if open source is going to stay a
sustainable phenomenon the same thing
goes for companies unless we understand
how to motivate outsiders they will have
a problem to embark on these open
innovation models that tend to propagate
amongst firms throughout firms and
industries now if we go back and think
about what really motivates the open
source developer in in in general there
are different perspectives on that what
is clear is that you can pay the
developer to contribute called
and here the motivation wouldn't be too
different from what you would find in
the company so people are extrinsically
motivated they would write open source
code to get their pay at the end of the
day and to make a career within
companies and plenty of studies actually
show that open source software
developers are
often extrinsically motivated on the
other hand side you have intrinsic
motivation in open source you have self
educational tasks meaning that you can
typically work on tasks that you find
very interesting and gratifying to work
on so rather than playing or rather than
responding to an external incentive you
actually respond to the fun and the joy
and the pleasure of doing a certain type
of work on a certain task
this is intrinsic motivation and I would
say that open-source software developers
today very often have a combination of
intrinsic and extrinsic motivation
driving them but sometimes for one of
the well know if you look more closely
at the what what drives them to develop
you also see for example that peer
recognition is critically important
unlearning people like to be recognized
for good software work amongst the peer
developers who they also respect and
they also like to engage with very smart
people in the open-source arena who give
feedback on the cold that they have
developed better or not did satisfy
certain quality criteria and lastly and
this is what we found in this recent
paper in Mis Q or V what they argued in
this recent paper and I'm is Q people
might actually be have a long-term drive
to create something which goes beyond
the short-term code or accomplishment or
code that they do but they want to
contribute as a live project to a larger
movement which is called the open source
movement and thereby also create
something that might be positive for the
software industry and positive for
customers and in some ways positive for
society what was kind of benefits to
companies getting from allowing their
employees to
yeah they get many benefits for example
they ensure that the open source
software that they run with a commercial
software for example or that they run on
their hardware that that they haven't
that they can ensure that the
development goes in a certain direction
they can ensure that some of the work
that they are actually doing in-house
can be tested and improved and refined
when they take it into the open source
project those are typical benefits they
can also benefit from for example a
reputation gained in in in the field of
software developers you can have
benefits such as for example teaching or
learning amongst your own software
developers so some people if you have a
software development team that works
with open source they can actually
experiment they can test their ideas
with the open source community and
that's kind of a low cost testbed for
software development compared to what
you would find internally I think that
what we have seen is kind of a book we
have seen as a very strong fragmentation
of the open source landscape and when I
say fragmentation I both mean the number
of new products that have been launched
that have increased tremendously over
the last couple years as well as a
tendency to fork the code base of
certain products making it sometimes
hard for developers to choose which
product to work on and I think this
increasing from fragmentation of open
source software can become a issue that
needs to be resolved for the future
sustainability of the phenomenon I think
it's not impossible to resolve it in the
sense that some of these products
they wither and die if they don't
attract sufficient development resources
but I'm a little concerned about the
obvious waste of resources that you find
in that process I'm also concerned that
some of the projects that would be would
not get sufficient attention and
attraction of development time and
resources that these projects might
actually have some innovation potential
in the sense that they could really be
radical represent radical innovations of
use for the Tuda software industry so
that I am most a little bit concerned
about I think what is positive and many
people in looking at open source said
that you know the companies start to get
involved with open source it is becoming
increasingly difficult to envision a
future in which open source can remain a
viable development model but I was never
that person istic or I sorry I'm not
that pessimistic I think that company
involvement in open source is very good
for the phenomenon because it
contributes to the sustainability of
projects because the companies have
customers who partly use open source and
therefore they have an interest also in
maintaining much of the codebase that
you find in some of these products you
think the open source development has
had yeah I think that the impact has
been his has been largely positive in
the sense that it has it has allowed
people to participate in software
development and learn about software
development who previously could not do
so I think that it has be given a lot of
of companies individuals access to
software of a certain quality that they
had previously not have either for
monetary reasons or because they were
simply not press
in the markets with these software is
very offered I think that it has shown
society that it is possible to combine
traditional intellectual property
regimes or patents and copyrights with
normal forms of open intellect open
regimes image you create public goods so
this private public combination private
good
combined with public goods that one is
highly interesting I think it it did the
model this private collective innovation
model that we see in open source
software has and will continue to have a
large impact on society good final
question what would you say like open
research questions now within management
science regarding the open source there
are a couple of important questions and
I think that the first question is to
understand the range of motivations of
open source software developers across
products we know a lot about individuals
in specific products but you don't know
too much about the full population of
open source software developers and the
full breadth of incentives that they
respond to and the full range of
motivations that dry them we have hard
until now a very narrow focus on on
extrinsic and intrinsic motivation but
it will be important to take into
account a full rain or much larger range
of motivational factors to understand
why they contribute thank you thank you
also pleasure
[Music]
thanks for listening to s-see radio an
educational program brought to you by I
Triple E software magazine for more
information about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at SES
radio net to support us you can
advertise su radio by clicking the Digg
reddit delicious or slash buttons on the
site or by talking about us on Facebook
Twitter or your own blog if you have
feedback specific to an episode please
use the commenting feature on the site
so that other listeners can respond to
your comments as well this and all of
the episodes of se radio is licensed
under the creative commons
two-point-five license please see the
website for details thanks again for
your support
[Music]
[Applause]